<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2025 Fall on McGill Statistics Seminars</title>
    <link>https://mcgillstat.github.io/tags/2025-fall/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 2025 Fall on McGill Statistics Seminars</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://mcgillstat.github.io/tags/2025-fall/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Convergence Guarantees for Adversarially Robust Classifiers</title>
      <link>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2025fall/2025-10-03/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2025fall/2025-10-03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;date-2025-10-03&#34;&gt;Date: 2025-10-03&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;time-1530-1630-montreal-time&#34;&gt;Time: 15:30-16:30 (Montreal time)&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;location-in-person-burnside-1104&#34;&gt;Location: In person, Burnside 1104&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;httpsmcgillzoomusj82469112499httpsmcgillzoomusj82469112499&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mcgill.zoom.us/j/82469112499&#34;&gt;https://mcgill.zoom.us/j/82469112499&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;meeting-id-824-6911-2499&#34;&gt;Meeting ID: 824 6911 2499&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;passcode-none&#34;&gt;Passcode: None&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Neural networks can be trained to classify images and achieve high levels of accuracy. However, researchers have discovered that well-targeted perturbations of an image can completely fool a trained classifier, even in cases where the modified image is visually indistinguishable from the original. This has sparked many new approaches to classification which include an adversary in the training process: such an adversary can improve robustness and generalization properties at the cost of decreased accuracy and increased training time. In this presentation, I will explore the connection between a certain class of adversarial training problems and the Bayes classification problem for binary classification. In particular, robustness can be encouraged by adding a regularizing nonlocal perimeter term, providing a strong connection to classical studies of perimeter. Borrowing tools from geometric measure theory, I will show the Hausdorff convergence of adversarially robust classifiers to Bayes classifiers as the strength of adversary decreases to 0. In this way, the theoretical results discussed in the presentation provide a rigorous comparison with the standard Bayes classification problem.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sparse Causal Learning: Challenges and Opportunities</title>
      <link>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2025fall/2025-09-26/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2025fall/2025-09-26/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;date-2025-09-26&#34;&gt;Date: 2025-09-26&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;time-1530-1630-montreal-time&#34;&gt;Time: 15:30-16:30 (Montreal time)&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;location-in-person-burnside-1104&#34;&gt;Location: In person, Burnside 1104&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;httpsmcgillzoomusj81200178578httpsmcgillzoomusj81200178578&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mcgill.zoom.us/j/81200178578&#34;&gt;https://mcgill.zoom.us/j/81200178578&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;meeting-id-812-0017-8578&#34;&gt;Meeting ID: 812 0017 8578&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;passcode-none&#34;&gt;Passcode: None&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In many observational studies, researchers are often interested in studying the effects of multiple exposures on a single outcome. Standard approaches for high-dimensional data such as the lasso assume the associations between the exposures and the outcome are sparse. These methods, however, do not estimate the causal effects in the presence of unmeasured confounding. In this paper, we consider an alternative approach that assumes the causal effects in view are sparse. We show that with sparse causation, the causal effects are identifiable even with unmeasured confounding. At the core of our proposal is a novel device, called the synthetic instrument, that in contrast to standard instrumental variables, can be constructed using the observed exposures directly. We show that under linear structural equation models, the problem of causal effect estimation can be formulated as an l0-penalization problem and hence can be solved efficiently using off-the-shelf software. Simulations show that our approach outperforms state-of-art methods in both low-dimensional and high-dimensional settings. We further illustrate our method using a mouse obesity dataset.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal vintage factor analysis with deflation varimax</title>
      <link>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2025fall/2025-09-19/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2025fall/2025-09-19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;date-2025-09-19&#34;&gt;Date: 2025-09-19&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;time-1530-1630-montreal-time&#34;&gt;Time: 15:30-16:30 (Montreal time)&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;location-in-person-burnside-1104&#34;&gt;Location: In person, Burnside 1104&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;httpsmcgillzoomusj83914219181httpsmcgillzoomusj83914219181&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mcgill.zoom.us/j/83914219181&#34;&gt;https://mcgill.zoom.us/j/83914219181&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;meeting-id-839-1421-9181&#34;&gt;Meeting ID: 839 1421 9181&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;passcode-none&#34;&gt;Passcode: None&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Vintage factor analysis is one important type of factor analysis that aims to first find a low-dimensional representation of the original data, and then to seek a rotation such that the rotated low-dimensional representation is scientifically meaningful. The most widely used vintage factor analysis is the Principal Component Analysis (PCA) followed by the varimax rotation. Despite its popularity, little theoretical guarantee can be provided to date mainly because varimax rotation requires to solve a non-convex optimization over the set of orthogonal matrices.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proper Correlation Coefficients for Nominal Random Variables</title>
      <link>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2025fall/2025-09-12/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2025fall/2025-09-12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;date-2025-09-12&#34;&gt;Date: 2025-09-12&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;time-1530-1630-montreal-time&#34;&gt;Time: 15:30-16:30 (Montreal time)&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;location-in-person-burnside-1104&#34;&gt;Location: In person, Burnside 1104&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;httpsmcgillzoomusj88021402798httpsmcgillzoomusj88021402798&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mcgill.zoom.us/j/88021402798&#34;&gt;https://mcgill.zoom.us/j/88021402798&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;meeting-id-880-2140-2798&#34;&gt;Meeting ID: 880 2140 2798&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;passcode-none&#34;&gt;Passcode: None&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This work develops an intuitive concept of perfect dependence between two variables of which at least one has a nominal scale that is attainable for all marginal distributions and proposes a set of dependence measures that are 1 if and only if this perfect dependence is satisfied. The advantages of these dependence measures relative to classical dependence measures like contingency coefficients, Goodman-Kruskal&amp;rsquo;s lambda and tau and the so-called uncertainty coefficient are twofold. Firstly, they are defined if one of the variables is real-valued and exhibits continuities. Secondly, they satisfy the property of attainability. That is, they can take all values in the interval [0,1] irrespective of the marginals involved. Both properties are not shared by the classical dependence measures which need two discrete marginal distributions and can in some situations yield values close to 0 even though the dependence is strong or even perfect.&#xA;Additionally, this work provide a consistent estimator for one of the new dependence measures together with its asymptotic distribution under independence as well as in the general case. This allows to construct confidence intervals and an independence test, whose finite sample performance is subsequently examine in a simulation study. Finally, we illustrate the use of the new dependence measure in two applications on the dependence between the variables country and income or country and religion, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
