<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2015 Fall on McGill Statistics Seminars</title>
    <link>/tags/2015-fall/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 2015 Fall on McGill Statistics Seminars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/2015-fall/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Causal discovery with confidence using invariance principles</title>
      <link>/post/2015fall/2015-12-10/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015fall/2015-12-10/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2015-12-10 Time: 15:30-16:30 Location: UdeM, Pav. Roger-Gaudry, salle S-116 Abstract: What is interesting about causal inference? One of the most compelling aspects is that any prediction under a causal model is valid in environments that are possibly very different to the environment used for inference. For example, variables can be actively changed and predictions will still be valid and useful. This invariance is very useful but still leaves open the difficult question of inference.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inference regarding within-family association in disease onset times under biased sampling schemes</title>
      <link>/post/2015fall/2015-11-26/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015fall/2015-11-26/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2015-11-26 Time: 15:30-16:30 Location: BURN 306 Abstract: In preliminary studies of the genetic basis for chronic conditions, interest routinely lies in the within-family dependence in disease status. When probands are selected from disease registries and their respective families are recruited, a variety of ascertainment bias-corrected methods of inference are available which are typically based on models for correlated binary data. This approach ignores the age that family members are at the time of assessment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prevalent cohort studies: Length-biased sampling with right censoring</title>
      <link>/post/2015fall/2015-11-13/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015fall/2015-11-13/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2015-11-13 Time: 15:30-16:30 Location: BURN 1205 Abstract: Logistic or other constraints often preclude the possibility of conducting incident cohort studies. A feasible alternative in such cases is to conduct a cross-sectional prevalent cohort study for which we recruit prevalent cases, i.e., subjects who have already experienced the initiating event, say the onset of a disease. When the interest lies in estimating the lifespan between the initiating event and a terminating event, say death for instance, such subjects may be followed prospectively until the terminating event or loss to follow-up, whichever happens first.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian analysis of non-identifiable models, with an example from epidemiology and biostatistics</title>
      <link>/post/2015fall/2015-11-06/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015fall/2015-11-06/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2015-11-06 Time: 15:30-16:30 Location: BURN 1205 Abstract: Most regression models in biostatistics assume identifiability, which means that each point in the parameter space corresponds to a unique likelihood function for the observable data. Recently there has been interest in Bayesian inference for non-identifiable models, which can better represent uncertainty in some contexts. One example is in the field of epidemiology, where the investigator is concerned with bias due to unmeasured confounders (omitted variables).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A knockoff filter for controlling the false discovery rate</title>
      <link>/post/2015fall/2015-10-30/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015fall/2015-10-30/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2015-10-30 Time: 16:00-17:00 Location: Salle 1360, Pavillon André-Aisenstadt, Université de Montréa Abstract: The big data era has created a new scientific paradigm: collect data first, ask questions later. Imagine that we observe a response variable together with a large number of potential explanatory variables, and would like to be able to discover which variables are truly associated with the response. At the same time, we need to know that the false discovery rate (FDR) - the expected fraction of false discoveries among all discoveries - is not too high, in order to assure the scientist that most of the discoveries are indeed true and replicable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robust mixture regression and outlier detection via penalized likelihood</title>
      <link>/post/2015fall/2015-10-23/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015fall/2015-10-23/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2015-10-23 Time: 15:30-16:30 Location: BURN 1205 Abstract: Finite mixture regression models have been widely used for modeling mixed regression relationships arising from a clustered and thus heterogenous population. The classical normal mixture model, despite of its simplicity and wide applicability, may fail dramatically in the presence of severe outliers. We propose a robust mixture regression approach based on a sparse, case-specific, and scale-dependent mean-shift parameterization, for simultaneously conducting outlier detection and robust parameter estimation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating high-dimensional multi-layered networks through penalized maximum likelihood</title>
      <link>/post/2015fall/2015-10-16/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015fall/2015-10-16/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2015-10-16 Time: 15:30-16:30 Location: BURN 1205 Abstract: Gaussian graphical models represent a good tool for capturing interactions between nodes represent the underlying random variables. However, in many applications in biology one is interested in modeling associations both between, as well as within molecular compartments (e.g., interactions between genes and proteins/metabolites). To this end, inferring multi-layered network structures from high-dimensional data provides insight into understanding the conditional relationships among nodes within layers, after adjusting for and quantifying the effects of nodes from other layers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parameter estimation of partial differential equations over irregular domains</title>
      <link>/post/2015fall/2015-10-09/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015fall/2015-10-09/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2015-10-09 Time: 15:30-16:30 Location: BURN 1205 Abstract: Spatio-temporal data are abundant in many scientific fields; examples include daily satellite images of the earth, hourly temperature readings from multiple weather stations, and the spread of an infectious disease over a particular region. In many instances the spatio-temporal data are accompanied by mathematical models expressed in terms of partial differential equations (PDEs). These PDEs determine the theoretical aspects of the behavior of the physical, chemical or biological phenomena considered.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating covariance matrices of intermediate size</title>
      <link>/post/2015fall/2015-10-02/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015fall/2015-10-02/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2015-10-02 Time: 15:30-16:30 Location: BURN 1205 Abstract: In finance, the covariance matrix of many assets is a key component of financial portfolio optimization and is usually estimated from historical data. Much research in the past decade has focused on improving estimation by studying the asymptotics of large covariance matrices in the so-called high-dimensional regime, where the dimension p grows at the same pace as the sample size n, and this approach has been very successful.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topics in statistical inference for the semiparametric elliptical copula model</title>
      <link>/post/2015fall/2015-09-25/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015fall/2015-09-25/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2015-09-25 Time: 15:30-16:30 Location: BURN 1205 Abstract: This talk addresses aspects of the statistical inference problem for the semiparametric elliptical copula model. The semiparametric elliptical copula model is the family of distributions whose dependence structures are specified by parametric elliptical copulas but whose marginal distributions are left unspecified. An elliptical copula is uniquely characterized by a characteristic generator and a copula correlation matrix Sigma. In the first part of this talk, I will consider the estimation of Sigma.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A unified algorithm for fitting penalized models with high-dimensional data</title>
      <link>/post/2015fall/2015-09-18/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015fall/2015-09-18/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2015-09-18 Time: 15:30-16:30 Location: BURN 1205 Abstract: In the light of high-dimensional problems, research on the penalized model has received much interest. Correspondingly, several algorithms have been developed for solving penalized high-dimensional models. I will describe fast and efficient unified algorithms for computing the solution path for a collection of penalized models. In particular, we will look at an algorithm for solving L1-penalized learning problems and an algorithm for solving group-lasso learning problems.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bias correction in multivariate extremes</title>
      <link>/post/2015fall/2015-09-11/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015fall/2015-09-11/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2015-09-11 Time: 15:30-16:30 Location: BURN 1205 Abstract: The estimation of the extremal dependence structure of a multivariate extreme-value distribution is spoiled by the impact of the bias, which increases with the number of observations used for the estimation. Already known in the univariate setting, the bias correction procedure is studied in this talk under the multivariate framework. New families of estimators of the stable tail dependence function are obtained.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>