<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2022 Winter on McGill Statistics Seminars</title>
    <link>https://mcgillstat.github.io/tags/2022-winter/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 2022 Winter on McGill Statistics Seminars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://mcgillstat.github.io/tags/2022-winter/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>New Approaches for Inference on Optimal Treatment Regimes</title>
      <link>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2022winter/2022-03-11/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2022winter/2022-03-11/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2022-03-11 Time: 15:30-16:30 (Montreal time) https://mcgill.zoom.us/j/83436686293?pwd=b0RmWmlXRXE3OWR6NlNIcWF5d0dJQT09 Meeting ID: 834 3668 6293 Passcode: 12345 Abstract: Finding the optimal treatment regime (or a series of sequential treatment regimes) based on individual characteristics has important applications in precision medicine. We propose two new approaches to quantify uncertainty in optimal treatment regime estimation. First, we consider inference in the model-free setting, which does not require specifying an outcome regression model. Existing model-free estimators for optimal treatment regimes are usually not suitable for the purpose of inference, because they either have nonstandard asymptotic distributions or do not necessarily guarantee consistent estimation of the parameter indexing the Bayes rule due to the use of surrogate loss.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Structure learning for extremal graphical models</title>
      <link>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2022winter/2022-02-18/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2022winter/2022-02-18/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2022-02-18 Time: 15:30-16:30 (Montreal time) https://umontreal.zoom.us/j/85105423917?pwd=enM3MGpFNkZKU2daMjRITmo0N0JUUT09 Meeting ID: 851 0542 3917 Passcode: 403790 Abstract: Extremal graphical models are sparse statistical models for multivariate extreme events. The underlying graph encodes conditional independencies and enables a visual interpretation of the complex extremal dependence structure. For the important case of tree models, we provide a data-driven methodology for learning the graphical structure. We show that sample versions of the extremal correlation and a new summary statistic, which we call the extremal variogram, can be used as weights for a minimum spanning tree to consistently recover the true underlying tree.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integration of multi-omics data for the discovery of novel regulators that modulate biological processes</title>
      <link>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2022winter/2022-02-11/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2022winter/2022-02-11/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2022-02-11 Time: 15:30-16:30 (Montreal time) https://mcgill.zoom.us/j/83436686293?pwd=b0RmWmlXRXE3OWR6NlNIcWF5d0dJQT09 Meeting ID: 834 3668 6293 Passcode: 12345 Abstract: The cellular states in various biological processes such as cell differentiation, disease progression, and treatment response are often enormously complex and thus hard to be profiled with unimodal profiling (e.g., transcriptome). Although those unimodal measurements had brought success for studies in a large variety of studies, the incomplete (and often misleading) unimodal cellular profiling could lead to biased and inaccurate conclusions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Off-Policy Confidence Interval Estimation with Confounded Markov Decision Process</title>
      <link>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2022winter/2022-02-04/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2022winter/2022-02-04/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2022-02-04 Time: 15:30-16:30 (Montreal time) https://mcgill.zoom.us/j/83436686293?pwd=b0RmWmlXRXE3OWR6NlNIcWF5d0dJQT09 Meeting ID: 834 3668 6293 Passcode: 12345 Abstract: In this talk, we consider constructing a confidence interval for a target policy’s value offline based on pre-collected observational data in infinite horizon settings. Most of the existing works assume no unmeasured variables exist that confound the observed actions. This assumption, however, is likely to be violated in real applications such as healthcare and technological industries.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Risk assessment, heavy tails, and asymmetric least squares techniques</title>
      <link>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2022winter/2022-01-28/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2022winter/2022-01-28/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2022-01-28 Time: 15:30-16:30 (Montreal time) https://umontreal.zoom.us/j/93983313215?pwd=clB6cUNsSjAvRmFMME1PblhkTUtsQT09 Meeting ID: 939 8331 3215 Passcode: 096952 Abstract: Statistical risk assessment, in particular in finance and insurance, requires estimating simple indicators to summarize the risk incurred in a given situation. Of most interest is to infer extreme levels of risk so as to be able to manage high-impact rare events such as extreme climate episodes or stock market crashes. A standard procedure in this context, whether in the academic, industrial or regulatory circles, is to estimate a well-chosen single quantile (or Value-at-Risk).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Change-point analysis for complex data structures</title>
      <link>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2022winter/2022-01-21/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2022winter/2022-01-21/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2022-01-21 Time: 15:30-16:30 (Montreal time) https://mcgill.zoom.us/j/83436686293?pwd=b0RmWmlXRXE3OWR6NlNIcWF5d0dJQT09 Meeting ID: 834 3668 6293 Passcode: 12345 Abstract: The change-point analysis is more than sixty years old. Over this long period, it has been an important subject of interest in many scientific disciplines such as finance and econometrics, bioinformatics and genomics, climatology, engineering, and technology.
In this talk, I will provide a general overview of the topic alongside some historical notes. I will then review the most recent and transformative advancements on the subject.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
