<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2014 Fall on McGill Statistics Seminars</title>
    <link>/tags/2014-fall/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 2014 Fall on McGill Statistics Seminars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/2014-fall/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Testing for structured Normal means</title>
      <link>/post/2014fall/2014-12-12/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014fall/2014-12-12/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2014-12-12 Time: 15:30-16:30 Location: BURN 1205 Abstract: We will discuss the detection of pattern in images and graphs from a high-dimensional Gaussian measurement. This problem is relevant to many applications including detecting anomalies in sensor and computer networks, large-scale surveillance, co-expressions in gene networks, disease outbreaks, etc. Beyond its wide applicability, structured Normal means detection serves as a case study in the difficulty of balancing computational complexity with statistical power.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Copula model selection: A statistical approach</title>
      <link>/post/2014fall/2014-12-05/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014fall/2014-12-05/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2014-12-05 Time: 15:30-16:30 Location: BURN 1205 Abstract: Copula model selection is an important problem because similar but differing copula models can offer different conclusions surrounding the dependence structure of random variables. Chen &amp;amp; Fan (2005) proposed a model selection method involving a statistical hypothesis test. The hypothesis test attempts to take into account the randomness of the AIC and other likelihood-based model selection methods for finite samples. Performance of the test compared to the more common approach of AIC is illustrated in a series of simulations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Model-based methods of classification with applications</title>
      <link>/post/2014fall/2014-11-28/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014fall/2014-11-28/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2014-11-28 Time: 15:30-16:30 Location: BURN 1205 Abstract: Model-based clustering via finite mixture models is a popular clustering method for finding hidden structures in data. The model is often assumed to be a finite mixture of multivariate normal distributions; however, flexible extensions have been developed over recent years. This talk demonstrates some methods employed in unsupervised, semi-supervised, and supervised classification that include skew-normal and skew-t mixture models. Both real and simulated data sets are used to demonstrate the efficacy of these techniques.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating by solving nonconvex programs: Statistical and computational guarantees</title>
      <link>/post/2014fall/2014-11-21/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014fall/2014-11-21/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2014-11-21 Time: 15:30-16:30 Location: BURN 1205 Abstract: Many statistical estimators are based on solving nonconvex programs. Although the practical performance of such methods is often excellent, the associated theory is frequently incomplete, due to the potential gaps between global and local optima. In this talk, we present theoretical results that apply to all local optima of various regularized M-estimators, where both loss and penalty functions are allowed to be nonconvex.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>High-dimensional phenomena in mathematical statistics and convex analysis</title>
      <link>/post/2014fall/2014-11-20/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014fall/2014-11-20/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2014-11-20 Time: 16:00-17:00 Location: CRM 1360 (U. de Montréal) Abstract: Statistical models in which the ambient dimension is of the same order or larger than the sample size arise frequently in different areas of science and engineering. Although high-dimensional models of this type date back to the work of Kolmogorov, they have been the subject of intensive study over the past decade, and have interesting connections to many branches of mathematics (including concentration of measure, random matrix theory, convex geometry, and information theory).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bridging the gap: A likelihood function approach for the analysis of ranking data</title>
      <link>/post/2014fall/2014-11-14/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014fall/2014-11-14/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2014-11-14 Time: 15:30-16:30 Location: BURN 1205 Abstract: In the parametric setting, the notion of a likelihood function forms the basis for the development of tests of hypotheses and estimation of parameters. Tests in connection with the analysis of variance stem entirely from considerations of the likelihood function. On the other hand, non- parametric procedures have generally been derived without any formal mechanism and are often the result of clever intuition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian regression with B-splines under combinations of shape constraints and smoothness properties</title>
      <link>/post/2014fall/2014-11-07/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014fall/2014-11-07/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2014-11-07 Time: 15:30-16:30 Location: BURN 1205 Abstract: We approach the problem of shape constrained regression from a Bayesian perspective. A B-spline basis is used to model the regression function. The smoothness of the regression function is controlled by the order of the B-splines and the shape is controlled by the shape of an associated control polygon. Controlling the shape of the control polygon reduces to some inequality constraints on the spline coefficients.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A copula-based model for risk aggregation</title>
      <link>/post/2014fall/2014-10-31/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014fall/2014-10-31/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2014-10-31 Time: 15:30-16:30 Location: BURN 1205 Abstract: A flexible approach is proposed for risk aggregation. The model consists of a tree structure, bivariate copulas, and marginal distributions. The construction relies on a conditional independence assumption whose implications are studied. Selection the tree structure, estimation and model validation are illustrated using data from a Canadian property and casualty insurance company.
Speaker Marie-Pier Côté is a PhD student in the Department of Mathematics and Statistics at McGill University.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PREMIER: Probabilistic error-correction using Markov inference in error reads</title>
      <link>/post/2014fall/2014-10-24/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014fall/2014-10-24/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2014-10-24 Time: 15:30-16:30 Location: BURN 1205 Abstract: Next generation sequencing (NGS) is a technology revolutionizing genetics and biology. Compared with the old Sanger sequencing method, the throughput is astounding and has fostered a slew of innovative sequencing applications. Unfortunately, the error rates are also higher, complicating many downstream analyses. For example, de novo assembly of genomes is less accurate and slower when reads include many errors. We develop a probabilistic model for NGS reads that can detect and correct errors without a reference genome and while flexibly modeling and estimating the error properties of the sequencing machine.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Patient privacy, big data, and specimen pooling: Using an old tool for new challenges</title>
      <link>/post/2014fall/2014-10-17/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014fall/2014-10-17/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2014-10-17 Time: 15:30-16:30 Location: BURN 1205 Abstract: In the recent past, electronic health records and distributed data networks emerged as a viable resource for medical and scientific research. As the use of confidential patient information from such sources become more common, maintaining privacy of patients is of utmost importance. For a binary disease outcome of interest, we show that the techniques of specimen pooling could be applied for analysis of large and/or distributed data while respecting patient privacy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A margin-free clustering algorithm appropriate for dependent maxima in the domain of attraction of an extreme-value copula</title>
      <link>/post/2014fall/2014-10-10/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014fall/2014-10-10/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2014-10-10 Time: 15:30-16:30 Location: BURN 1205 Abstract: Extracting relevant information in complex spatial-temporal data sets is of paramount importance in statistical climatology. This is especially true when identifying spatial dependencies between quantitative extremes like heavy rainfall. The paper of Bernard et al. (2013) develops a fast and simple clustering algorithm for finding spatial patterns appropriate for extremes. They develop their algorithm by adapting multivariate extreme-value theory to the context of spatial clustering.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistical exploratory data analysis in the modern era</title>
      <link>/post/2014fall/2014-10-03/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014fall/2014-10-03/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2014-10-03 Time: 15:30-16:30 Location: BURN 1205 Abstract: Major challenges arising from today&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;data deluge&amp;rdquo; include how to handle the commonly occurring situation of different types of variables (say, continuous and categorical) being simultaneously measured, as well as how to assess the accompanying flood of questions. Based on information theory, a bias-corrected mutual information (BCMI) measure of association that is valid and estimable between all basic types of variables has been proposed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of palliative care studies with joint models for quality-of-life measures and survival</title>
      <link>/post/2014fall/2014-09-26/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014fall/2014-09-26/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2014-09-26 Time: 15:30-16:30 Location: BURN 1205 Abstract: In palliative care studies, the primary outcomes are often health related quality of life measures (HRLQ). Randomized trials and prospective cohorts typically recruit patients with advanced stage of disease and follow them until death or end of the study. An important feature of such studies is that, by design, some patients, but not all, are likely to die during the course of the study.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Covariates missing by design</title>
      <link>/post/2014fall/2014-09-19/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014fall/2014-09-19/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2014-09-19 Time: 15:30-16:30 Location: BURN 1205 Abstract: Incomplete data can arise in many different situations for many different reasons. Sometimes the data may be incomplete for reasons beyond the control of the experimenter. However, it is also possible that this missingness is part of the study design. By using a two-phase sampling approach where only a small sub-sample gives complete information, it is possible to greatly reduce the cost of a study and still obtain precise estimates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hydrological applications with the functional data analysis framework</title>
      <link>/post/2014fall/2014-09-12/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014fall/2014-09-12/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2014-09-12 Time: 15:30-16:30 Location: BURN 1205 Abstract: River flows records are an essential data source for a variety of hydrological applications including the prevention of flood risks and as well as the planning and management of water resources. A hydrograph is a graphical representation of the temporal variation of flow over a period of time (continuously measured, usually over a year). A flood hydrograph is commonly characterized by a number of features, mainly its peak, volume and duration.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>