<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2019 Winter on McGill Statistics Seminars</title>
    <link>/tags/2019-winter/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 2019 Winter on McGill Statistics Seminars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/2019-winter/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Patient-Specific Finite Element Analysis of Human Heart: Mathematical and Statistical Opportunities and Challenges</title>
      <link>/post/2019winter/2019-02-08/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2019winter/2019-02-08/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2019-02-08 Time: 15:30-16:30 Location: BURN 1104 Abstract: Cardiovascular diseases (CVD) are the leading cause of death globally and ranks second in Canada, costing the Canadian economy over $20 billion every year. Despite the recent progress in CVD through prevention, lifestyle changes, and the use of biomedical treatments to improve survival rates and quality of life, there has been a lack in the integration of computer-aided engineering (CAE) in this field.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modern Non-Problems in Optimization: Applications to Statistics and Machine Learning</title>
      <link>/post/2019winter/2019-01-25/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2019winter/2019-01-25/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2019-01-25 Time: 16:00-17:00 Location: BURN 920 Abstract: We have witnessed a lot of exciting development of data science in recent years. From the perspective of optimization, many modern data-science problems involve some basic ``non’’-properties that lack systematic treatment by the current approaches for the sake of the computation convenience. These non-properties include the coupling of the non-convexity, non-differentiability and non-determinism. In this talk, we present rigorous computational methods for solving two typical non-problems: the piecewise linear regression and the feed-forward deep neural network.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Singularities of the information matrix and longitudinal data with change points</title>
      <link>/post/2019winter/2019-01-18/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2019winter/2019-01-18/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2019-01-18 Time: 15:30-16:30 Location: BURN 1205 Abstract: Non-singularity of the information matrix plays a key role in model identification and the asymptotic theory of statistics. For many statistical models, however, this condition seems virtually impossible to verify. An example of such models is a class of mixture models associated with multi-path change-point problems (MCP) which can model longitudinal data with change points. The MCP models are similar in nature to mixture-of-experts models in machine learning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Magic Cross-Validation Theory for Large-Margin Classification</title>
      <link>/post/2019winter/2019-01-11/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2019winter/2019-01-11/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2019-01-11 Time: 15:30-16:30 Location: BURN 1205 Abstract: Cross-validation (CV) is perhaps the most widely used tool for tuning supervised machine learning algorithms in order to achieve better generalization error rate. In this paper, we focus on leave-one-out cross-validation (LOOCV) for the support vector machine (SVM) and related algorithms. We first address two wide-spreading misconceptions on LOOCV. We show that LOOCV, ten-fold, and five-fold CV are actually well-matched in estimating the generalization error, and the computation speed of LOOCV is not necessarily slower than that of ten-fold and five-fold CV.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>