<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2024 Fall on McGill Statistics Seminars</title>
    <link>https://mcgillstat.github.io/tags/2024-fall/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 2024 Fall on McGill Statistics Seminars</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://mcgillstat.github.io/tags/2024-fall/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A latent-vine factor-copula time series model for extreme flood insurance losses</title>
      <link>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2024fall/2024-11-08/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2024fall/2024-11-08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;date-2024-11-08&#34;&gt;Date: 2024-11-08&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;time-1530-1630-montreal-time&#34;&gt;Time: 15:30-16:30 (Montreal time)&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;location-in-person-burnside-1104&#34;&gt;Location: In person, Burnside 1104&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;httpsmcgillzoomusj89121567327httpsmcgillzoomusj89121567327&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mcgill.zoom.us/j/89121567327&#34;&gt;https://mcgill.zoom.us/j/89121567327&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;meeting-id-891-2156-7327&#34;&gt;Meeting ID: 891 2156 7327&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;passcode-none&#34;&gt;Passcode: None&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Vines and factor copula models are handy tools for statistical inference in high dimension. However, their use for assessing and predicting the co-occurrence of rare events is subject to caution when multivariate extreme data are sparse. Motivated by the need to assess the risk of concurrent large insurance claims in the American National Flood Insurance Program (NFIP), I will describe a novel class of copula models that can account for spatio-temporal dependence within clustered sets of time series. This new class, which combines the advantages of vines and factor copula models, provides great flexibility in capturing tail dependence while maintaining interpretability through a parsimonious latent structure. Using NFIP data, I will show the value of this approach in evaluating the risks associated with extreme weather events.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Mixture of Experts in Large-Scale Statistical Machine Learning Applications</title>
      <link>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2024fall/2024-11-01/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2024fall/2024-11-01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;date-2024-11-01&#34;&gt;Date: 2024-11-01&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;time-1530-1630-montreal-time&#34;&gt;Time: 15:30-16:30 (Montreal time)&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;location-in-person-burnside-1104&#34;&gt;Location: In person, Burnside 1104&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;httpsmcgillzoomusj81284191962httpsmcgillzoomusj81284191962&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mcgill.zoom.us/j/81284191962&#34;&gt;https://mcgill.zoom.us/j/81284191962&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;meeting-id-812-8419-1962&#34;&gt;Meeting ID: 812 8419 1962&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;passcode-none&#34;&gt;Passcode: None&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Mixtures of experts (MoEs), a class of statistical machine learning models that combine multiple models, known as experts, to form more complex and accurate models, have been combined&#xA;into deep learning architectures to improve the ability of these architectures and AI models to capture the heterogeneity of the data and to scale up these architectures without increasing the computational&#xA;cost. In mixtures of experts, each expert specializes in a different aspect of the data, which is then combined with a gating function to produce the final output. Therefore, parameter and expert estimates&#xA;play a crucial role by enabling statisticians and data scientists to articulate and make sense of the diverse patterns present in the data. However, the statistical behaviors of parameters and experts in a mixture&#xA;of experts have remained unsolved, which is due to the complex interaction between gating function and expert parameters.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Statistical Methods and Quality Control for Industry 4.0</title>
      <link>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2024fall/2024-10-25/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2024fall/2024-10-25/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;date-2024-10-25&#34;&gt;Date: 2024-10-25&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;time-1530-1630-montreal-time&#34;&gt;Time: 15:30-16:30 (Montreal time)&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;location-online-retransmitted-in-burnside-1104&#34;&gt;Location: Online, retransmitted in Burnside 1104&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;httpsmcgillzoomusj81908885431httpsmcgillzoomusj81908885431&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mcgill.zoom.us/j/81908885431&#34;&gt;https://mcgill.zoom.us/j/81908885431&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;meeting-id-819-0888-5431&#34;&gt;Meeting ID: 819 0888 5431&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;passcode-none&#34;&gt;Passcode: None&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Statistical and machine learning techniques have emerged as powerful tools in Industry 4.0 to benefit from the increasing availability of sensors and data and enable informed decision-making and process optimization. This seminar will provide an overview of several industrial applications in high-dimensional settings developed by the Statistics for Engineering Research (SFERe) group (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sfere.unina.it&#34;&gt;www.sfere.unina.it&lt;/a&gt;), affiliated with the Department of Industrial Engineering at the University of Naples FEDERICO II. In these applications, the definition and use of novel statistical methods have been a competitive advantage for naval, automotive, and rail companies. The open-source R software packages implementing these methods will also be mentioned to highlight their accessibility and potential applicability in different industrial contexts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A functional data approach for statistical shapes analysis</title>
      <link>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2024fall/2024-10-11/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2024fall/2024-10-11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;date-2024-10-11&#34;&gt;Date: 2024-10-11&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;time-1530-1630-montreal-time&#34;&gt;Time: 15:30-16:30 (Montreal time)&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;location-in-person-burnside-1104&#34;&gt;Location: In person, Burnside 1104&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;httpsmcgillzoomusj87824357176httpsmcgillzoomusj87824357176&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mcgill.zoom.us/j/87824357176&#34;&gt;https://mcgill.zoom.us/j/87824357176&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;meeting-id-878-2435-7176&#34;&gt;Meeting ID: 878 2435 7176&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;passcode-none&#34;&gt;Passcode: None&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The shape $\tilde{\mathbf{X}}$ of a random planar curve, $\mathbf{X}$, is what remains when the deformation variables (scaling, rotation, translation, and reparametrization) are removed. Previous studies in statistical shape analysis have focused on analyzing $\tilde{\bf X}$ through discrete observations of ${\bf X}$. While this approach has some computational advantages, it overlooks the continuous nature of variables: $\tilde{\bf X}$, ${\bf X}$, and it ignores the potential dependence of deformation variables on each other and $\tilde{ \bf X}$, which results in a loss of information in the data structure. I will introduce a new framework for studying $\bf X$ based on functional data analysis in this presentation. Basis expansion techniques are employed to find analytic solutions for deformation variables such as rotation and parametrization deformations. Then, the generative model of $\bf X$ is investigated using a joint-principal component analysis approach. Numerical experiments on synthetic and real datasets demonstrate how this new approach performs better at analyzing random planar curves than traditional functional data methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VCBART: Bayesian trees for varying coefficients</title>
      <link>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2024fall/2024-09-27/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2024fall/2024-09-27/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;date-2024-09-27&#34;&gt;Date: 2024-09-27&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;time-1530-1630-montreal-time&#34;&gt;Time: 15:30-16:30 (Montreal time)&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;location-online-retransmitted-in-burnside-1104&#34;&gt;Location: Online, retransmitted in Burnside 1104&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;httpsmcgillzoomusj88350756970httpsmcgillzoomusj88350756970&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mcgill.zoom.us/j/88350756970&#34;&gt;https://mcgill.zoom.us/j/88350756970&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;meeting-id-883-5075-6970&#34;&gt;Meeting ID: 883 5075 6970&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;passcode-none&#34;&gt;Passcode: None&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The linear varying coefficient models posits a linear relationship between an outcome and covariates in which the covariate effects are modeled as functions of additional effect modifiers. Despite a long history of study and use in statistics and econometrics, state-of-the-art varying coefficient modeling methods cannot accommodate multivariate effect modifiers without imposing restrictive functional form assumptions or involving computationally intensive hyperparameter tuning. In response, we introduce VCBART which flexibly estimates the covariate effect in a varying coefficient model using Bayesian Additive Regression Trees. With simple default settings, VCBART outperforms existing varying coefficient methods in terms of covariate effect estimation, uncertainty quantification, and outcome prediction. Theoretically, we show that the VCBART posterior contracts at the near-minimax optimal rate. Finally, we illustrate the utility of VCBART through simulation studies and a real data application examining how the association between later-life cognition and measures of socioeconomic position vary with respect to age and sociodemographics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variance reduction by occluding a Markov chain</title>
      <link>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2024fall/2024-09-20/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2024fall/2024-09-20/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;date-2024-09-20&#34;&gt;Date: 2024-09-20&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;time-1530-1630-montreal-time&#34;&gt;Time: 15:30-16:30 (Montreal time)&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;location-in-person-burnside-1104&#34;&gt;Location: In person, Burnside 1104&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;httpsmcgillzoomusj88265323185httpsmcgillzoomusj88265323185&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mcgill.zoom.us/j/88265323185&#34;&gt;https://mcgill.zoom.us/j/88265323185&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;meeting-id-882-6532-3185&#34;&gt;Meeting ID: 882 6532 3185&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;passcode-none&#34;&gt;Passcode: None&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Stochastic algorithms which simulate random variables/processes on a computer to estimate intractable quantities are ubiquitous in Statistics and elsewhere. One such method is Markov chain Monte Carlo which, under mild conditions, offer asymptotical (in time) guarantees. In this talk, we define infinitely many stopping times at which an ergodic Markov chain is occluded by a (conditionally) independent process. The resulting process, called the occluded process, is not Markov, but provided that the stopping times/independent process are cleverly defined, we show that it is ergodic. One particularly powerful way to define the stopping times/independent process leverages the recent advances in ML regarding approximations of probability distributions (divergence minimization, normalizing flows, etc.). We discuss the variance reduction effect of the occluded process through some illustrations and (weak) theoretical results in some limiting regime.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
