<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2024 Fall on McGill Statistics Seminars</title>
    <link>https://mcgillstat.github.io/tags/2024-fall/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 2024 Fall on McGill Statistics Seminars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://mcgillstat.github.io/tags/2024-fall/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A functional data approach for statistical shapes analysis</title>
      <link>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2024fall/2024-10-11/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2024fall/2024-10-11/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2024-10-11 Time: 15:30-16:30 (Montreal time) Location: In person, Burnside 1104 https://mcgill.zoom.us/j/87824357176 Meeting ID: 878 2435 7176 Passcode: None Abstract: The shape $\tilde{\mathbf{X}}$ of a random planar curve, $\mathbf{X}$, is what remains when the deformation variables (scaling, rotation, translation, and reparametrization) are removed. Previous studies in statistical shape analysis have focused on analyzing $\tilde{\bf X}$ through discrete observations of ${\bf X}$. While this approach has some computational advantages, it overlooks the continuous nature of variables: $\tilde{\bf X}$, ${\bf X}$, and it ignores the potential dependence of deformation variables on each other and $\tilde{ \bf X}$, which results in a loss of information in the data structure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>VCBART: Bayesian trees for varying coefficients</title>
      <link>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2024fall/2024-09-27/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2024fall/2024-09-27/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2024-09-27 Time: 15:30-16:30 (Montreal time) Location: Online, retransmitted in Burnside 1104 https://mcgill.zoom.us/j/88350756970 Meeting ID: 883 5075 6970 Passcode: None Abstract: The linear varying coefficient models posits a linear relationship between an outcome and covariates in which the covariate effects are modeled as functions of additional effect modifiers. Despite a long history of study and use in statistics and econometrics, state-of-the-art varying coefficient modeling methods cannot accommodate multivariate effect modifiers without imposing restrictive functional form assumptions or involving computationally intensive hyperparameter tuning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Variance reduction by occluding a Markov chain</title>
      <link>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2024fall/2024-09-20/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mcgillstat.github.io/post/2024fall/2024-09-20/</guid>
      <description>Date: 2024-09-20 Time: 15:30-16:30 (Montreal time) Location: In person, Burnside 1104 https://mcgill.zoom.us/j/88265323185 Meeting ID: 882 6532 3185 Passcode: None Abstract: Stochastic algorithms which simulate random variables/processes on a computer to estimate intractable quantities are ubiquitous in Statistics and elsewhere. One such method is Markov chain Monte Carlo which, under mild conditions, offer asymptotical (in time) guarantees. In this talk, we define infinitely many stopping times at which an ergodic Markov chain is occluded by a (conditionally) independent process.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
